Now, let's look at the history of the AWS cloud, so it was launched in 2002 internally
at Amazon.com because they realized that the IT department could be externalized.
So their Amazon infrastructure was one of their core strength and they said, "You know what?
Maybe we can do IT for someone else, for other people." So they launched their first offering
publicly, which was SQS in 2004. In 2006, they expanded their offering and they relaunched
with the availability of SQS, S3 and EC2. Don't worry, we'll see all these services in this course.
Then the expenditure said, "You know what? We don't have to be just in America. We could be in Europe."
And then, fast forward to today, we have so many applications that used to run or are still running
on AWS, such as Dropbox, Netflix, Airbnb, or even the NASA. Now, let's look at where AWS is today.
If you look at the magic quadrant from Gartner, you can see that AWS is a leader.
And it has been the case for many, many years. So, AWS now has $90 billion in revenue
as of 2023 and it accounts for about 31% of the market in Q1, 2024, with Microsoft being second
with 25%. It's been a pioneer and a leader of the market for 13th consecutive years
and it has over 1 million active users. So, learning AWS really sets you up for success
in the cloud world. So, what can you build on AWS? Well, pretty much everything.
AWS will enable you to build sophisticated and scalable applications and they are applicable
to a diverse set of industries. Every company has a use case for the cloud.
So, Netflix, McDonald's, 21st Century Fox, Activision, they're all using the cloud.
And use cases can include just transferring your enterprise IT or using the cloud as a backup
in storage or doing some big data analytics. You can also host a website or create a backend
for your mobile and your social applications. Or, you can have your entire gaming servers
running on the cloud. The applications are endless. Now, AWS is global and this is where we
are going to learn a bit more specifics about how it works. So, we have AWS regions,
we have availability zones, data centers, edge locations and points of presence and all of these
can be represented on the map right here. So, let's go on this website to have a quick look at it.
So, this is a cool map because on this website we can see how AWS is global. So, if I click on it,
I can scroll the world and see what is happening. So, we can see that AWS has multiple regions
and they're in orange and they're all around the world. For example, Paris and Spain and Ohio
in Sao Paulo, Cape Town, Mumbai and everywhere else. So, AWS truly is a global service. On top of
it, each region are going to be connected through the network. So, these are the network reconnecting
the regions and this is a private network of AWS. And then, within each region, for example,
if I really scroll into the Cape Town region, we can see that we have blue dots and each
blue dots will be available to zones that we'll be describing in the next slide. So, as we can see,
what I want to get you out of this is that AWS truly is global and we can leverage the infrastructure
of the cloud provider to make ourselves our application global. The first important concept in AWS
are regions. So, regions are all around the world and we saw it on the map from before.
The regions have a name. It could be us east one, EU west three and we can see the mapping of the
name of the region to their code on the console that we'll see in a minute. Now, a region
what is in its truly? Well, it's going to be a cluster of data centers. So, many different data centers
located near, for example, Ohio or Singapore or Sydney or Tokyo. When we use AWS services,
most services are going to be linked and scoped to a specific region. That means that if we use a
service in one region and we try to use it in another region, it will be like a new time of
using the service. Now, a question that may come up in the exam is how do you choose an AWS region?
So, say you're launching a new application, where should you do it? Should you do it in America,
in Europe, in South America or in Australia? Well, the answer is, of course, it depends.
But let's look at some factors that may impact your choice of an AWS region. The first one
is compliance. So, sometimes governments want the data to be local to the country you're deploying
the application in. For example, friends, data in France may have to stay in France and therefore
you should launch your application in the French region. Then, there is also a concept of latency.
So, if most of users are going to be in America, it makes a lot of sense to deploy your application
in America close to your users, because they will have a reduced latency. If you deploy your
application in Australia and your users are in America, they will have a lot of lag at using your
application. Then, also, not all regions have all services. Some regions do not have services, and so,
obviously, if you're leveraging a service with your application, you need to make sure that the
region you're deploying into is available and does have that service. And finally, pricing. So, pricing
does vary from region to region, and you need to consult the services pricing pages to see what
the differences are between the regions, but this could be obviously a factor that could impact
your deployment of an application into a specific region. Now, availability zones are what actually
are going into the region. So, each region will have many availability zones. Usually, three,
the minimum is three, and the max is six, but really, the usual is three. So, let's take the Sydney
region as an example. The Sydney region code is AP South East 2. So, we have three availability
zones in Sydney. AP South East 2a, AP Southeast 2b, and AP Southeast 2c. Now, each of these availability
zones are going to be one or more discrete data centers that will have redundant power, networking,
and connectivity. That means that in Southeast 2a, I can have two data centers, maybe as well
two in 2b and two in 2c, but it could be one, it could be three, it could be four, we don't really
know. It always doesn't tell us that. But what we know is that these availability zones are
separate from each other so that they will be isolated from disasters. So, if something happens to
AP Southeast 2a, we know that it is designed not to cascade into AP Southeast 2b or AP Southeast 2c. So,
they're really isolated from disasters. And then, these data centers, these availability zones,
they are connected with a high bandwidth, ultra low latency networking, and therefore,
altogether being linked together, it will form a region. Okay, next, the only thing we need to know
about AWS for the global infrastructure is the points of presence or edge locations.
We will see them in details in the global section of this course, but you should know that AWS
has more than 400 points of presence in 90 cities across 40 countries, and this will be very
helpful when we deliver content to the end users with the lowest latency possible. And this is what
you see on this map. Now, again, I'm going quickly over this because we will see this at the about
the middle of this course. So, now, how about we just play around and do a tour of the console?
We'll see that AWS has global services, such as IAM, around 53, Cloudfront, and WAF, but we'll see
that also most AWS services are going to be regionscoped, such as Amazon EC2, Elastic Beanstalk,
Lambda, and recognition. Finally, to know if a service is available in your region,
there is a region table you should take out right here.